<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A narrative of the adventures of Lewis Marott pilot-royal of the galleys of France. Giving an account of his slavery under the Turks, his escapes out of it, and other strange occurrences that ensued thereafter. Translated from the French copy.</title>
            <title>Relation de quelques aventures maritimes de L.M.P.R.D.G.D.F. English.</title>
            <author>Marot, Louis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70693</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N174</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19964</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834835</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834835</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39407</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70693)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39407)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 643:18 or 1993:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A narrative of the adventures of Lewis Marott pilot-royal of the galleys of France. Giving an account of his slavery under the Turks, his escapes out of it, and other strange occurrences that ensued thereafter. Translated from the French copy.</title>
                  <title>Relation de quelques aventures maritimes de L.M.P.R.D.G.D.F. English.</title>
                  <author>Marot, Louis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 86 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Edward Brewster, at the Crane in St. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An English translation of: Marot, Louis.  Relation de quelques aventures maritimes de L.M.P.R.D.G.D.F.</note>
                  <note>Errata on verso of final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Identifed as Wing (2nd ed.) N174 at 643:18, and as M706B (entry cancelled in Wing 2nd ed.) at 1993:18.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Bodleian Library ("Early English books, 1641-1700" reel 643), and the Harvard University Library (reel 1993).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marot, Louis --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39407:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39407:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NARRATIVE OF THE <hi>Adventures</hi> OF <hi>LEWIS MAROTT,</hi> PILOT-ROYAL OF The Galleys of <hi>FRANCE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Giving an Account of his Slavery under the <hi>Turks,</hi> his Eſcapes out of it, and other ſtrange occurrences that enſued thereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated from the French Copy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Edward Brewſter,</hi> at the <hi>Crane</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1677.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:39407:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:39407:2"/>
            <head>A Narrative of the Adventures of <hi>LEWIS MAROTT,</hi> Pilot Royal of <hi>France,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the time when His <hi>Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty,</hi> the preſent <hi>French King,</hi> was in <hi>Provence,</hi> an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer of the late deceaſed Queen-Mother, walking in the principal place of <hi>Arles,</hi> where the Court was at that time, perceived a man, who by his habit of a Mariner, by his ſhort hair, his great Muſtachoes, and his tan'd countenance, made him judg, that he was neither of that Town, nor
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:39407:3"/>one belonging to the Court: and for as much as he earneſtly look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon all thoſe which were then a walking there, he ſeemed to look about whether he could not know ſome one or other there: which occaſioned the aforeſaid Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer more diligently to conſider him; which when he had done, he imagin'd that he had ſeen him in ſome place heretofore. And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards coming nearer to him, he demanded of him, Whether he had ever been in <hi>Barbary?</hi> Several times (replied this unknown per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon); but (purſued he) did I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſee you at <hi>Tunis?</hi> At that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry word the tone of his voice, and ſome lineaments of his viſage, made him remember it was Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Marot,</hi> with whom he had
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:39407:3"/>been ſome time at the Conſuls of <hi>Tunis</hi> about eight years ſince. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the mutual embraces of one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, the aforeſaid Officer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to underſtand of him, that he was come from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Arles</hi> with Letters of Recommendation from Cardinal <hi>Antonio</hi> to Cardinal <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarine,</hi> to try if he could obtain the place or office of Pilot-Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of the Galleys belonging to the <hi>French</hi> King, thought that he ought to aſſiſt him to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of his power, at leaſtwiſe to get him ſome acquaintance and friendſhip in a Court, where he knew not to whom he might ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs himſelf to be introduced. And as he remembred, <hi>Marot</hi> had heretofore made the recital to him of his extraordinary Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39407:4"/>he doubted not but this might be a very fit means whereby he might win the friendſhip of thoſe whom he might have need of. This obliged him to bring him to dinner to the Office of the Queens Gentlemen of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, where he preſented him to the company as one of his moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar friends, and as one that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be ſuccoured in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity which his Courage and the traverſes of his life had caſt him into.</p>
            <p>All of them gave him a very good reception; and being prom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted by curioſity, they asked him many Queſtions, which he could not immediately reſolve; which was the occaſion that for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of the whole Company
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:39407:4"/>at one and the ſame time, ſo ſoon as Dinner was done, he made relation of his whole Hiſtory near upon the matter in theſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry words.</p>
            <p>I Am <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, born in the Town of <hi>Ciontat:</hi> My Parents were ſuch as had more Honour for their patrimony, than Goods of Fortune. And foraſmuch as I had always a particular inclination to the Sea, I was not above ten or twelve years old, when I made my firſt Voyage, which was to <hi>Alexandretta,</hi> in a <hi>Polach</hi> of <hi>Cion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat.</hi> After I had ſerved ſome years as <hi>Mouſſy,</hi> that is to ſay, Captains Boy; conſidering the ſmall For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune I was like to meet with in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39407:5"/>my Fathers Houſe, I took up a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to endeavour to obtain mine by the Sea, which, as you know, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> is the true thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Fortune.</hi> And foraſmuch as the way to make ones ſelf capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of higher employments, is to begin by ſuch as are lower and more laborious; I entred my ſelf as Mariner in a Veſſel that was bound for <hi>Alexandria.</hi> This Voyage was followed by many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for the moſt part ſuccesful; inſomuch that I had already got ſomething whereof to make ſome ſmall beginning of Traſlique by a Voyage from <hi>Alexandret</hi> to <hi>France.</hi> We were therein about thirty men, as well Mariners as paſſengers; our Navigation was ſuccesful enough, till we came to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:39407:5"/>
               <hi>Maltha,</hi> where we ſounded; there the Chevalier <hi>de Bois Bandrand,</hi> having a mind to return from thence into <hi>France,</hi> embarqued in our ſhip.</p>
            <p>Steering our courſe very ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, we perceived one morning four ſail that gave us the chaſe; we were not above four leagues from the ſmall Iſland of <hi>Africa,</hi> called <hi>Pantellerie,</hi> where the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition of the ſeaſon was ſo contrary to us, and ſo favourable to our purſuers, that though we were becalmed, yet they had a very good wind; inſomuch that they approached near to us with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a Cannon-ſhot, in leſs than two hours.</p>
            <p>Knowing them now at laſt to be <hi>Corſairs</hi> of <hi>Tunis,</hi> we diſpoſed our
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39407:6"/>ſelves to the Combat, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the great inequality of our Forces: All of us took up a reſolution rather to loſe our lives than our liberty.</p>
            <p>Immediately they attacqued us, and plyed us ſo well with their Cannon, that after we had enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſome ten hours, many of our men being dead, our Veſſel al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt having loſt all her tackling, and being ready to ſink, they boarded us at laſt, and became Maſters of our ſhip.</p>
            <p>When I ſaw the fury of the firſt onſet was great, and that the <hi>Turks</hi> although they were already Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the ſhip, <hi>baſtinado'd</hi> the firſt Chriſtians that they got into their hands; I climbed up ſpeedily to the top of the Main Maſt. I let half an
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39407:6"/>hour paſs, they not perceiving all the while that I was there. Seeing now that all was appeaſed, and that they began to think upon remedying the diſorders of the ſhip, I put my ſelf in a poſture of working; and hearing that many of them called the chief Commander <hi>Muſtapha Raiz,</hi> I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo tender'd my ſelf to him, and calling him by the ſame name, demanded of him, if it ſhould pleaſe him I ſhould do ſuch or ſuch a thing. Now I knew well enough that it was convenient to do it at that time, inſomuch as he ſaid to me, <hi>Do it preſently.</hi> I made uſe of this ſtratagem, that ſo coming into their hands not till their fury was over, and till I had made my ſelf known to them,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39407:7"/>and qualified them by ſome ſmall ſervice that I did for them, I might avoid their <hi>Baſtinadoes</hi> that I ſo ſtood in fear of. This ſucceeded ſo well to me, that I was in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the only perſon that was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from their cruel treatments.</p>
            <p>After we were all chained, the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Veſſel and the Prize made ſale towards <hi>Tunis;</hi> where, ſo ſoon as we were arrived, we were parted amongſt thoſe that were ſharers, as being owners of the Pirate ſhip. The Baſhaw choſe me for his Dividend, and ſent me into a place called the <hi>Bath,</hi> which is in a manner a little Cloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, wherein he kept good ſtore of ſlaves; I found there ſome of my Comrades; and for as much as I have always had the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39407:7"/>of being well known, ſome Merchants of <hi>Provence</hi> which were at <hi>Tunis,</hi> coming to hear of my misfortune, came to ſee me, and one amongſt them lent me ſeven or eight <hi>Piaſters.</hi> This ſmall ſum of money did marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly accommodate me, and gave me the occaſion of helping the <hi>Chevalier de Bois Brandrand,</hi> and my other Comrades, the greateſt part of which being much wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and without any money, were in a moſt miſerable condition. That I might ſucceed in this affair the more proſitably for them, and the more commodiouſly for my ſelf, I asked the favour of the Guardian <hi>Bachy</hi> of the <hi>Bath,</hi> to give me leave to do what I could toward the getting of ſomething
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:39407:8"/>whereby I might help them, that ſo they might be recovered from their wounds the ſooner.</p>
            <p>He having given me this liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I beſtowed five or ſix <hi>Piaſters</hi> in <hi>Tobacco,</hi> and ſome other ſmall trifles, which I ſold by retail. God bleſſed my ſmall Trade in ſuch a manner, that in a very few days I ſaw my money doubled. And for as much as I am a man of that humour, that what I gain eaſily, I ſpend in like ſort, I got together one day the aforeſaid <hi>Chevalier,</hi> my Captain, and ſeven or eight of the principal of our Comrades, and brought them to a Tavern to make merry, and paid for them all, and afterwards gave them over and above each one a <hi>Piaſter.</hi> We were in this condition, when the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:39407:8"/>Galleys of <hi>Algiers</hi> touched in at <hi>Tunis,</hi> to go to the <hi>Levant;</hi> and in regard that we belonged to the <hi>Levantines,</hi> they gave us to them of <hi>Algiers,</hi> who promiſed them in exchange, to go to the Coaſts of <hi>Italy,</hi> to take ſome ſlaves of thoſe Countreys, and to re-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them the ſame number; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that our <hi>Patrons,</hi> willing to return to the <hi>Levant,</hi> had rather have <hi>Italians</hi> than us. So now we are all in Galleys, except the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid <hi>Chevalier,</hi> who remained in chains at <hi>Tunis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Galleys of <hi>Algiers</hi> and <hi>Tunis</hi> being ten in number, ſet forth, and arrived together at the Coaſts of <hi>Calabria,</hi> and by the Counſel of a Runnagate of that Countrey they ſurprized by night
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39407:9"/>a ſmall Town called <hi>Otaya,</hi> they ſacked it, and pillaged it, and made ſlaves of all that could not ſave themſelves by flight. In all my life I never ſaw a like deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; all was halled pell mell into the Galleys. Great ſtore of Monks and Nuns had the ſame treatments; even many Infants that were yet at the breaſts, were made Captives before they knew what liberty was.</p>
            <p>The Galleys having ſailed up and down near the ſhore for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt the ſpace of a day, waited, if any of the neighbouring places would come to redeem any one, according to the cuſtom. But no body coming, whether it were for want of money, or charity, or elſe that there were hardly any more
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:39407:9"/>perſons upon that Coaſt, they took towards the <hi>Levant,</hi> and carried away all thoſe miſerable and unfortunate people.</p>
            <p>Our Voyage was very quiet till we came to <hi>Valone,</hi> where the Chriſtian Army having ſurprized thoſe ten Galleys of <hi>Barbary,</hi> they were conſtrained, as all <hi>Europe</hi> knows, to fall upon the ſhelves or quickſands; where after they had landed us all, they left the Galleys to the Chriſtians, and conducted us all to <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> There it was that theſe new ſlaves were ſold, excepting two fair Damoſels that were preſented to the Grand Seignior.</p>
            <p>For my part, falling into the hands of one <hi>Murdat,</hi> or <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat,</hi> at that time Baſſa of <hi>Cyprus,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:39407:10"/>I was put in a Galley, which parted thence ſhortly after with ſome others for the Sea.</p>
            <p>Several years paſt, that I was continually in this miſery; Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages were often made: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am afraid of troubling you too much, if I ſhould rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon up all the particularities, I will come to the moſt important point of all my Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>Twelve years had lingred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſince the loſs of my liberty; neither did I find my ſelf as yet in any likelihood of being able to recover it. Now the Galley in which I was, meeting with four others of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> in the parts of <hi>Alexandria</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> thoſe that had the command of it, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a mind to refreſh themſelves
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:39407:10"/>there for ſome weeks, cauſed all the Oars to be carried to the Magazines that are near the Port, that thereby they might take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all occaſions from the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians of laying any deſign for their flight.</p>
            <p>Theſe neceſſary means being taken away from them, and all the ſlaves being under the chains, except the Scribes, the Captains were alſo without fear of any ſuch thing happening, and only left about twenty Soldiers for the guard of each Galley.</p>
            <p>Long it was that I had medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated upon ſome means for ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf alone, or at leaſtwiſe with ſome few of my Comrades, but I found no poſſibility thereof. That ſmall knowledg which God
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39407:11"/>had given me for the affairs of the Sea, had always been hurtful to me; and my Patron loving me as being a neceſſary perſon to him, oft told me, that I ſhould never hope to return into my Country, and that he would have me dye with him. Moreover, knowing me to be of an active ſpirit, and fit for contriving any thing, he made me be looked to more narrowly than the reſt; inſomuch that I did not know almoſt either what to do or think. I ſaw nothing whereon to found any hope of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty: and conſidering with my ſelf that I was to paſs the reſt of my life at the Oar, thoſe long years preſented themſelves to me, being accompanied with ſo many inevitable miſeries, that if it had
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39407:11"/>not been for the apprehenſion of changing them into greater, I had endeavoured to terminate them by giving my ſelf death. This thought alone, I ſay, of being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways chained to a Galley, bruiſed with blows, ill fed, almoſt naked, expoſed to the rigors of cold and heat, and never to lye in a bed, did ſo incenſe my Courage to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize all that I could for my deliverance from theſe miſeries, that thoſe deſigns which were leaſt poſſible and moſt perillous, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me eaſie and without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            <p>Under this conſideration it was, that I enterprized to make an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection among the <hi>Chiourmes</hi> of the five Galleys, and to cauſe them all to embarque in one.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:39407:12"/>I confeſs at firſt I was aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the greatneſs of this Deſign, and the difficulty of executing it. To which much was added by the improbability that I foreſaw there would be to keep the ſecret, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that ſo many ſlaves of divers Nations, of different Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, of Religions and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours oppoſite one to another, could be well inſtructed therein, and come to an agreement about the means and time of the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an Enterprize ſo perillous. But being fully reſolved to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge my ſelf, to ſave my ſelf, or to dye, I put all to the hazzard, having nothing to fear the loſs of.</p>
            <p>I had always done whatſoever I was able, to make my ſelf belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:39407:12"/>of the Soldiers, and by the Slaves that were ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r to the Bench that I belonged to. The which that I might the better effect, I gave them part of thoſe dryed fruits, and other trifles, that the Captain of the <hi>Provincial</hi> ſhips had heretofore given me. Yea, and foraſmuch as I had from time to time ſent me from my Countrey ſome moneys, I alſo treated theſe Companions of my miſery, ſo that they commonly called me in that Galley, <hi>The Rich Slave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now about this time, and in the conjuncture whereof I have ſpoken, having by good fortune ſome money by me, I invited all the <hi>Scribes</hi> of the Galleys to come on <hi>Friday</hi> to dine with me at my Bench, that ſo under this
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:39407:13"/>pretence I might diſcover to them my deſign with more eaſe and leſs danger of ſuſpition. The Scribes (as I told you) are without any other Irons but one ſhackle upon their legs, that ſo they may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble freely to perform their functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. They failed not to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout noon-tide, which was the hour that I had appointed them. There was near us a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier that narrowly watched us, and who being not willing to let us meet together thus, but upon condition that we ſpake always the <hi>Frank</hi> Tongue, which he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, troubled us much, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that he not leaving us one minute, I could not propoſe my affair to my Gueſts: I thought it expedient therefore, that to make
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:39407:13"/>him the leſs ſevere an obſerver of our diſcourſe, and of our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, it were beſt to engage him to dine with us, which he did without any great invitation. All dinner long (which continued a pretty while) there paſt ſeveral diſcourſes of our Adventures and Combats; which was ſo far from advancing my affair, that it ſpent that time which I deſtined to make a declaration thereof unto them; inſomuch that I deſpaired almoſt of diſcovering any thing that day; whenas God put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my mind to take out a Prayer-book called the Hours of our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which I had in my Packet: and turning my ſelf to the <hi>Turk,</hi> who having dined <hi>gratis,</hi> was of the beſt humour imaginable: <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtapha</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:39407:14"/>(ſaid I unto him, for ſo he was called), <hi>we Chriſtians have a Cuſtom amongst us, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we meet together, to ſay certain prayers which our Religion orders us: wilt thou give us leave at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to pray to God out of this book? with all my heart</hi> (replied he) <hi>pray as much as thou wilt.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he took the Flaggon, and drank once more a good draught of Wine, although according to his Religion it was counted a great ſin. Then ſeeing my ſelf in a good way, I opened my book, and ſaid in the <hi>Arabick</hi> Tongue, <hi>Biſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mylah,</hi> which ſigniſies <hi>In the name of God.</hi> At this word the <hi>Turk</hi> touching his Turbant, ſaid, <hi>Ah good word!</hi> I went on, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a ſhew of reading (mine
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:39407:14"/>eyes being fixed upon my Book) I ſaid in our Countrey Language (which the <hi>Turk</hi> did no ways un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, and which the moſt part of my Companions underſtood in a competent manner): <hi>My dear Comrades, I made uſe of the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this repaſt, to communicate to you a deſign whereon our liberty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends. If you approve of it, to every propoſition that I ſhall make, ſay, with a bow of your head at the ſame time,</hi> Em challah, <hi>that is to ſay, And it pleaſe God. And if you ſhall find any thing which you think cannot, or ought not to be done, you ſhall ſay</hi> Straffilla, <hi>which is as much as to ſay, God forbid: and ſo afterwards, I ſhall propoſe other means according to your li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. By this ſtratagem we may
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:39407:15"/>(under pretence of praying to God) deceive this Turk that ſpies our actions: And I am apt to think, that hearing us oft pronounce that adorable Name, and ſeeing us lift up our eyes to Heaven, he will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be perſwaded that we are in this holy exerciſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon I propoſed to them all the Enterpriſe in the order that I had projected it, and in what manner, and when it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed good to me to execute it. All which was ſo conformable to their ſentiments, that at every article lifting up their eyes towards Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, they ſaid all with one conſent, <hi>Einthalla.</hi> Even the <hi>Turk</hi> himſelf, being mollified by the very pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers which he thought we made, put himſelf into a poſture of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39407:15"/>praying after his faſhion, ſaying, <hi>Allah he ill allah Mehemned Reſall allah;</hi> that is to ſay in <hi>Arabick, There is no other God but God, and</hi> Mahomet <hi>his Prophet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After dinner the <hi>Scribes</hi> return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed each one to his Galley, and as we had agreed among our ſelves, communicated the Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe in groſs only to the <hi>Voga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vans</hi> (or chief Rowers) of each Bench, enjoining them to keep the Secret till <hi>Friday</hi> following, when they might diſcover it to all the reſt of the Slaves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Friday</hi> amongſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> is what <hi>Sunday</hi> is amongſt the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. Now it was the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the time which theſe Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels employ in Praying in their <hi>Moſches,</hi> or Temples, which made
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:39407:16"/>us chuſe it as more fit than any other for this our deſign.</p>
            <p>This day ſo much deſired, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arrived, and a little while af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thoſe who from the top of their Towers are appointed to call the people together, had ceaſed, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the greateſt part of the <hi>Turks</hi> were at their Prayers; I aroſe bolt upright upon the higheſt part of the Bench that I belonged to, and cryed out many times with all my might, <hi>Vive St</hi> Jean <hi>&amp; fuora Cadena,</hi> for that was the word we had agreed upon Upon this very moment the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>250 ſlaves of the <hi>Levant</hi> readily repeated the ſame words, crying out in a horrible manner, and making a moſt dreadful noiſe with their Chains, they laid hold of all the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:39407:16"/>
               <hi>Agabys</hi> or ſticks that ſupport the Tents of the Galleys, and ruſhing with fury upon the Soldiers, knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down all them that put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a poſture of defence. The reſt being ſurpriſed, and troubled at the unlooked-for inſurrection, caſt themſelves in a deſperate manner into the Sea, and intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that pittileſs Element with their Lives and Liberties, which we wou'd have taken from them. In the mean while the Scribes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaining in great haſte the <hi>Voga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> in regard they were the ſtronger, and part of them unlooſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Chains of their Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whilſt the others ſight againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> in leſs than half a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an hour the five <hi>Chiourmes,</hi> or five Seats or Benches of Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:39407:17"/>were freed from their Fetters. Then it was that this good begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning putting courage into all their hearts, in a little while they fully defeated the Guardians of the Galleys.</p>
            <p>This being done, we laid hold of their <hi>Cimeters,</hi> and thoſe who had none, provided themſelves of ſticks, <hi>Agaby's,</hi> and pieces of the Baniſters of the Galleys which we had broken.</p>
            <p>When I ſaw that they were all ready, I cryed as loud as I could, <hi>Fuora.</hi> At this inſtant we went out of the Galleys excepting 100 men, who ſtayed to guard that wherein we were reſolved to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark our ſelves.</p>
            <p>All the Sentinels in the mean time having ſeen our Combat
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:39407:17"/>from the top of their Towers, had advertiſed the Town thereof, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as at the moment we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to march towards the Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zin, the Cannon of the Caſtles and of the Town were diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon us, but ſlew few of our men; the oppoſition that we found at the dore of the Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zin, was much more great. About 200 <hi>Turks</hi> that were moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in our flight, were come forth of the City firſt of all, and by a continual firing of their Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, killed above a hundred of our men in a trice. Nevertheleſs for all their reſiſtance, we ſo invelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped them, that I believe there hardly eſcaped ten of them.</p>
            <p>Afterwards the dore of the Magazine being forced open, 200
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:39407:18"/>of our men loaded themſelves with ſifty pair of Oars. Thoſe that remained, made an alley, by ſtanding in two ranks, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to march in the middle of us with all ſpeed imaginable. Now it was, that the <hi>Turks</hi> run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thick-and-threefold out of the Town, and coming upon us, put us almoſt in a condition of being able to go no further: The Combat began again afreſh much more furiouſly than before. Store of our people, even thoſe that carried the Oars, fell down dead by their continual firing. But in regard that we fought not only for liberty, but alſo to ſhun thoſe horrible puniſhments which we were ſure to bear if we fell again into their hands, it is no wonder
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:39407:18"/>if we paſſed through every diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty that oppoſed our March. And although the enemies were much more than we, and encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed every moment, yet we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred (in deſpight of all their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to the contrary) into our Galley, after that we had killed above four or five hundred of their men. It is true, that an equal number of ours, near upon the matter, lay dead alſo upon the place.</p>
            <p>Being now embarqued, about Eight hundred of us, the Oars were fitted with an incredible promptitude, and with a thouſand ſhouts of joy we began to Row with a fury that can't be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended.</p>
            <p>What an agreeable ſpectacle
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:39407:19"/>was it for us to ſee all the people of <hi>Alexandria</hi> run together to the ſhore-ſide? What joy was it to us, to ſee our ſelves free by ſo honourable an Adventure, and to revenge our ſelves in this manner of them who had cauſed us to ſuffer ſo much, thus robbing them of that which was moſt dear to them? But this beginning was too happy for ſlaves: the conſequence muſt be attended with a different ſucceſs, to moderate the exceſs of our joy.</p>
            <p>We ſet forwards with the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport and efforts of Fugitives: We were already almoſt out of Cannon-ſhot, whenas with one ſhot which came from a Tower, the Main-Maſt of our Galley was cut off, and fell into the Sea.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:39407:19"/>Immediately ſeven or eight of us betook our ſelves to one of the ſmall Boats attending upon the Galley, to regain and ſit this piece which was ſo important to us.</p>
            <p>While we were in this employ, thoſe of our people who govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Cannon, having a mind to fire as frequently as they could, charged with ſo much precipitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they ſcattered up and down in the Galley almoſt as much powder as they made uſe of; inſomuch as when they were firing againſt the Town, it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened by ſad misfortune, that the fire of our Cannon getting hold of the powder which was ſcatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up and down, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards alſo of ſome Barrels of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:39407:20"/>powder which were not far off; the Galley was in a moment all on a fire. Thoſe which were at the Stern above us, thinking all loſt, betook themſelves to the ſmall Boat with us.</p>
            <p>In this confuſion we were ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the Galley a pretty handſome diſtance; and that which contributed to our ruine, was, that a great wind aroſe, which drave us back towards the Haven; and night came on apace, which robbed us of the ſight of the Galley.</p>
            <p>In this ſtrange extremity, any condition ſeemed more tolerable to us, than that of returning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſtate of ſlaves. We ſailed with ſo much force, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the fury of the wind,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:39407:20"/>which was contrary to us, we made a ſhift to reach the main Ocean.</p>
            <p>About midnight we perceived near us a Barque of the ſame bulk with ours, and which went the ſame way. After that we were ſome time in doubt what it might be, we at length knew that it was our ſecond Cague or ſmall Boat, wherein many of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany had caſt themſelves, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our fortune, and to avoid the peril wherein they thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be by the fire, which took hold of the Galley; which nevertheleſs was not much enda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maged, and was ſaved (as after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards we came to underſtand) in <hi>Candy,</hi> with the reſt of the ſlaves that were therein. And foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the Sea was very rough
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:39407:21"/>and tempeſtuous, we durſt not come near one another, only we cried one to another as loud as we could, that we ſhould not ſeparate our ſelves, but keep the ſame way.</p>
            <p>Thus we continued our courſe forwards, although it were with very great difficulty. The break of day beginning to appear, we hoped that the weather would become more favourable; but far from this good luck, the wind en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed rather about Sun-riſing; inſomuch as whatever we could do (it being impoſſible for us to keep our courſe) we were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to ſtrike ſail, and leave our ſelves wholly to the mercy of the wind, vvhich caſt us upon a place called <hi>Cape Blanc,</hi> ſome few leagues from <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:39407:21"/>there ſplit our Veſſel.</p>
            <p>What ſudden change was this; of ſo advantageous and favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a beginning! Scarcely did we ſet ſight of our Liberty, but ſhe fled away from us, and left us in the Country of our very Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, of our Judges, and of our Maſters, from whom we expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed little compaſſion in our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. We were ſo caſt down and troubled, as well with this conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, as with our wearineſs and hunger, that we were near upon an hour lying upon the ground, before we teſtified any care either of life or death, of liberty or ſlavery.</p>
            <p>At laſt a <hi>Vogavant</hi> that was of <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> being a very ſturdy and courageous fellow, riſing up, <hi>My
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:39407:22"/>Companions</hi> (ſaid he), <hi>never had we more need of a good heart, than at preſent: we muſt arm our ſelves with reſolution: there is nothing loſt if we will but labour with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence. Of our two Barks which you ſee ſplit there, we may make one which may contain us all: and as for victuals, thoſe that are the ſtronger amongſt us, muſt go and ſearch out for ſome upon the Land, though it be with the peril of their life. Courage there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, my Brethren, and let us not ſuffer our ſelves to be caſt down with ſorrow, which can't reſtore us our liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This diſcourſe cauſed us to recollect our ſelves a little, and to take heart. All of us roſe up, and having made a review
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:39407:22"/>of our company, we found our ſelves to be fourſcore and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen, whereof fifty were ſent to ſeek out for Proviſion under the conduct of the <hi>Ruſſian,</hi> whilſt the reſt were employed to gather together the reliques of our ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack, and make thereof one Barque, which was almoſt in a condition to be made uſe of that very evening.</p>
            <p>Whenas our company returned from their queſt of proviſion, the Countrey thereabouts being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, &amp; uninhabited, they b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ought back nothing but Dates and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robs (or St. <hi>Johns</hi> bread) and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fruits of the Countrey, and that in ſo ſmall a quantity, that it could not ſerve at the furtheſt for above three days, for ſo many
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:39407:23"/>as we were. The next day the Tempeſt being much encreaſed, and there not being any likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood that it would quickly ceaſe, we were in an inexplicable trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble about what courſe we ſhould take.</p>
            <p>The Barque was made ready, as much as the weather, the place, and the want of Utenſils and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſary things would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. But to ſet forth to Sea at ſuch a time as it was, this was to precipitate our ſelves to a certain death: and then on the other hand, to wait till the wind chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, it was no leſs perillous. For it was thought (and truly we were not deceived therein) that in all probability our Patrons ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the danger we were in, would
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:39407:23"/>be eaſily perſwaded that we ſhould either return back, or be caſt upon ſome coaſts of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and that ſo they would not fail to ſend in the queſt of us. To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> had been to ſeek out our execution; and if we ſhould leave the Sea, and take our journey ſouthward, we ſhould caſt our ſelves into the hands of certain <hi>Alarbes,</hi> Hereticks of the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Religion, that hold it as an article of their faith, That he amongſt them that kills a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> infallibly gains Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice. What muſt we do then? After much conſideration it was at laſt reſolved, that it being the ſureſt way to leave <hi>Alexandria</hi> as much as we could, we ſhould ſet forward towards <hi>Tripolis</hi> of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bary,</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:39407:24"/>along that Coaſt; and that we ſhould leave the common Road a little on one ſide, and that we ſhould take our marches only by night.</p>
            <p>Thus it was determined, and thus executed. We left therefore our Bark behind us, and took our journey vvith that ſmall proviſion vvhich vve had. Some propoſed it as expedient to go and get more firſt; but for fear of being diſcovered if vve ſhould ſtay longer in that Countrey, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a hope of finding more of thoſe fruits in our journey, vve neglected this advice, vvhich ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs vve repented of a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times afterward. For at the end of three or four days, we ſaw, together with the end of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:39407:24"/>our miſery commence a-new more cruel than ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. The more we ſet forwards, the more vve found the Countrey deſert, dry, and deſtitute of all Commodities; no Water, no Fruits, no Inhabitants, but Lyons, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and other the like furious creatures. In a word, vve vvere reduced to that extremity, that vve muſt eat nothing but graſs during ſome days: and thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vveakned by this ill nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as alſo the vvant of vvater, and the tireſomneſs of our jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, ſtill as vve vvent along, there continually dyed ſome one or other of our company, of them vvhich vvere of the vveakeſt conſtitution; inſomuch that the eighth or ninth day after our ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvrack,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:39407:25"/>there vvas remaining not above eight and tvventy of the fourſcore and thirteen that vve vvere at firſt. The hunger and cruelty of ſome <hi>Ruſſians</hi> that vvere in our company, vvas ſo great, that having perceived a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>Negro</hi> that ran avvay from them, and clambered up a high rock to ſave himſelf, vvhen they had at laſt caught hold of him, they cut him into morſels, and roaſted him by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in the Sun, and aftervvards eat him.</p>
            <p>Thus ſtill advancing tovvards <hi>Tripoli,</hi> vve began to find the ſoil more freſh and graſſy, vvhich made us think that there vvas Water not far off. To conclude, making to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvards tvvo great <hi>Palm</hi>-trees
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:39407:25"/>which were on the left hand, five or ſix hundred paces from the Sea, we found there-under a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fair ſpring of freſh water, and very clear; thus with a joy that can't be explained, we quenched our thirſt, and reſted our ſelves above three hours.</p>
            <p>At the very moment that we were ready to part thence, and to purſue our journey, we percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the ſide of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> a body of Horſe which made to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us: we eaſily imagining what it might be, thought our ſelves utterly undone if we were diſcovered: and foraſmuch as the coaſt thereabouts where we lay, was deſtitute of any thing that might favour our flight without being perceived, we concluded
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:39407:26"/>that we muſt continue lying cloſe in the ſame poſture as we were, and that it may be thoſe people might paſs by without ſeeing of us: in effect, we ſaw them make their way upon the ſhore ſide, without turning in the leaſt to that ſide on which we were.</p>
            <p>They were already over-againſt us, or rather ſomewhat beyond us: We ſaid one to another, <hi>Now we are ſafe.</hi> But at this very moment we ſaw two Horſe-men ſeparate themſelves from the reſt of the Troop, and come a hand-gallop towards us.</p>
            <p>Now therefore judging either our flight or defence to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, we put our ſelves in a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture neither of the one nor of the other. Thus theſe Soldiers
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:39407:26"/>having perceived us, and knowing us to be thoſe that they looked for, make a ſign to the reſt of the Troop to come on; and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately one of the two, whom I knew to be a Runagate of <hi>Ci-four</hi> in <hi>Provence,</hi> ſaid to us, <hi>Ah poor wretches! your fortune had been much leſs cruel, if you had ſunk to the bottom of the Sea in the midſt of the Tempeſt, than to fall again into our hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Scarce had he made an end of this fair complement, when the whole Body invironed us, calling us a thouſand <hi>Rogues</hi> and <hi>Raſcals,</hi> and teſtifying a very great joy for having found us again. Thoſe that were the moſt devout of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, went aſide, and performed their <hi>Sala,</hi> which is their ordinary
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:39407:27"/>prayer, to thank <hi>Mahomet</hi> for this happy ſucceſs of their ſearch.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Barbarians,</hi> which were about 150 (and the ſame num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber were gone, as we underſtood, on the other ſide <hi>Alexandria,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Roſette</hi>) bound us imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately; that is to ſay, our hands behind our backs. And after they had dined, and reſted themſelves about an hour, and had given us ſome Beans, which we eat upon the ground, like horſes, being not able to make uſe of our hands: They loaded us four and four in a company upon Camels, two on each ſide, as Faggots.</p>
            <p>In this deadly poſture, ſome hours paſt in journeying along: but at laſt theſe cruel guides per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that many amongſt us
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:39407:27"/>were not able to continue long in this poſture without being killed, ſet us upon the ground, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding us to follow them a foot, although we were indeed very weak and tired. The fear of being put upon the Camels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, made us force our ſelves as much as we could, inſomuch that at the beginning we travelled pretty well But becauſe their Horſes and Camels went a good pace, we could not reſiſt a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs which quite overwhelmed us; ſo that we were fain to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to the <hi>Turks, That it was impoſſible for us to follow them:</hi> And they imagining that blows would do that upon us which ſpurs did to their Horſes, they gave us good ſtore of Baſtinadoes
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:39407:28"/>for to make us march on the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. Our weakneſs having ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd this violent remedy unuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, they were at laſt conſtrained to let us travel in ſuch manner as the condition vvherein vve were would permit us to do. Many days were paſt wherein we had travelled eight or ten leagues a day, not having any thing elſe but Beans for our ſuſtenance, which we eat as I told you upon the ground, after the ſame manner as Horſes eat their Oats.</p>
            <p>Being arrived at a place vvhere ſome of the <hi>Arabes</hi> had their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence, they ſtaid to make their repaſt, and reſt themſelves at a <hi>Dowars</hi> vvhich vvas not far off. The <hi>Dowars</hi> in <hi>Africa</hi> are for the moſt part fourſcore or a hundred
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:39407:28"/>Tents made of Goats hair, ranked in order very near to one another, and ſet round in ſuch a manner, that they take up a great deal of ground by their circumference. Under each Tent dwells a Family of the <hi>Alarbes;</hi> and their whole ſociety is as it vvere a movable Tovvn: for in regard there are in thoſe Countreys great ſtore of vvaſte Lands, and uninhabited, vvhen they are a vveary of ſtaying in one place, they go to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>It was in one of theſe <hi>Dowars</hi> that vve ſtaid, as I told you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. The Men and the Women are all naked, vvithout teſtifying any ſign of ſhame thereof. We vvere a little aſtoniſhed thereat, foraſmuch as it vvas a thing not
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:39407:29"/>very ordinary in thoſe coaſts. But our miſeries vvere at ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, that vve little conſidered thoſe of others, neither had any liſt to trouble our ſelves vvith thoſe things that did not concern us.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as ever theſe <hi>Alarbes</hi> ſavv us in a condition ſo deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, they gave us to underſtand that they had pity of us; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the Women (vvho are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly more compaſſionate than the men in all places) tenderly pitied us, and made vvhat haſte they could to bring us ſomething to eat. Their Charity truly vvas very abundant tovvard us. It had been a long time vve had eaten nothing that vvas either good or warm, inſomuch that we filled our
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:39407:29"/>bellies ſo full with many pots of good Rice which they had ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, that we were e'ne ready to burſt; and if the want of food had before made us ſick, for this time the exceſs of it made us ſo much more; nevertheleſs there was not one of us that dyed.</p>
            <p>This our journey continued under our ordinary ſufferings, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til we came to <hi>Pompeys Pillar,</hi> which is not far from <hi>Alexandria.</hi> There while they ſtayed to reſt themſelves and eat, a Horſeman went to the City, to carry the news of our recovery, inſomuch that a great number of people of both Sexes, and all ages, came to meet us out of curioſity, and for to revile us. The Wives and Children, and other kinsfolk of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:39407:30"/>thoſe we had killed in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, were the firſt of all; and being not content to overwhelm us with revilings, they had alſo ſtoned us to death, if the <hi>Turks</hi> that conducted us, had not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd them.</p>
            <p>At laſt we arrived at the City, being as well tormented with the Hues and Cryes of the people, as with the Severities that were paſt, and with the fear of what was to to come. So ſoon as we were all made ſafe, and had our chains put upon our legs, we were ſince told, that thoſe that were intereſted in our return, held a Councel; and foraſmuch as the paſſions of theſe people were different, the advices of what they ſhould do with us, were different alſo: Thoſe that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:39407:30"/>were rich and cruel, concluded upon our death, and preferred the pleaſure of revenging themſelves, before a ſmall advantage of their own. Thoſe amongſt the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſted perſons that were poor or covetous, being not able fully to ſatisfie their revenge, without do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves ſome inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in regard of their profit, gave counſel that they ſhould ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinado us, but that with ſuch mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, that the Fugitives might be puniſhed, and their profit pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. Some others being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more kind in appearance, but in effect no whit leſs cruel, ſaid, that we were puniſhed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough by the evils which our ſlight had cauſed us to ſuffer; and that if ſo be there wanted any
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:39407:31"/>thing to the expiation of our Crimes, the labours either of the Earth or of the Galleys might make it up. My <hi>Patron,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of the moſt powerful a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, at laſt re-united all their opinions in his own, which was to ſend us back to the Oars, to make us find our puniſhments in ſerving of them, more than ever we had done before.</p>
            <p>Now behold we are again at the Oars; after ſome days im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the preparation of our departure from thence, we ſailed ſlowly towards the <hi>Archipelago.</hi> During this Voyage, we began to repent of our flight, by reaſon of the doubling of our labour and blows, and the cutting of us ſhort in our ordinary proviſion.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:39407:31"/>This cruel treatment was the cauſe that when we arrived at <hi>Pacomo,</hi> a ſmall deſert Iſland, neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Anatolia,</hi> we were the moſt part of us nothing but skin and bones.</p>
            <p>We anchored in a kind of Gulf, whoſe Banks were of an eaſie acceſs, and covered with Woods that were pretty thick: And foraſmuch as the mind of one that is in ſlavery, is hardly ever employed about any thing ſo much, as the ſeeking out of ſome way or means of ſaving himſelf; it is not a thing to be wondred at, if I meditated on a ſecond flight, being founded on the circumſtances of the place and night that now approached. All ſeemed eaſie to me, provided
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:39407:32"/>I were but freed of my Chains; and this indeed was the greateſt difficulty, and the moſt important point, in regard that I deſpaired in a manner ever to accompliſh it for want of Utenſils neceſſary hereunto. Nevertheleſs, feeling my Legs, I perceived that my Patrons ſeverity in his puniſhing me by ſo many Baſtinadoes, and my faſting, had even given me a means of unchaining my ſelf.</p>
            <p>In effect, the night being come, and it being very dark, command was given that every one ſhould take his ſhort Night-Coat, and go to ſleep. And in regard that while they are a preparing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for this purpoſe, there is commonly a great noiſe and hurly-burly in the Galley, I took occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:39407:32"/>after I had put on my Night-Coat, to try what I could do (during that clinking of chains) to get my foot looſe from mine: I ſucceeded well therein, but not without great pain to my ſelf, by reaſon of the ankle bone that hinder'd my Chains from coming off.</p>
            <p>This done, I put my ſelf in ſuch a poſture as the reſt were in, but with a deſign of employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf to a much better pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. You know (Sirs) that there belongs to each Bench a place with a very large hole for the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the body; the only li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty that is given us in the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys to move any where, is to go to this place when we have occaſion; and it is for this purpoſe alſo that
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:39407:33"/>the Chain is as long as the Bench. Now therefore ſo ſoon as I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that all were aſleep ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting the Sentinels, who uſually are no where elſe but at the fore or hin-deck, I roſe up to go to this place, crying, out as loud as I could, <hi>Ala banda</hi> (this is the word with which they are to give notice of it, upon pain of being baſtinado'd).</p>
            <p>Being therefore ſeated thereon, I gently lift up<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> my Night-Coat by little and little, ſomewhat higher than my head; and ſo ſtaying it upon two ſmall ſticks, which I fixed upon two planks, I found that it could ſtand ſo without my aid, and that by the favour of the night it might eaſily deceive the eyes even of the Sentinels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves:
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:39407:33"/>this conceit being fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in ſuch a ſort, that it ſeemed to be my ſelf all the while, and did likewiſe hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them from ſeeing what I did underneath. Firſt I got my Legs through, afterwards all the reſt of my body, without any great difficulty; and afterwards ſwimming with as little noiſe as I could (and as ſoftly, we being between two waters), I happily at laſt got to land without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perceived in the leaſt, leaving behind me my Night-Coat, which without doubt was ſeverely threatned with Baſtinadoes for being too long upon the Stool.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as I came to land,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:39407:34"/>I betook my ſelf as ſoon as poſſibly I could to the Wood to hide my ſelf therein, and to wait for the day, which appeared a little while after; for it was about that time of the year when the nights are the ſhorteſt. Afterwards ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king my progreſs continually from the place where I left the Galleys, in a few hours I perceived my ſelf on t'other ſide of the Iſle; and I was ſo lucky, as to meet with a Veſſel of <hi>Maltha</hi> that had ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived there to take in water, the Captain of which took me aboard with a teſtification of much joy, and gave me both Clothes and other things, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I had great need: for when
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:39407:34"/>I took my flight, I had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing on me but my Galley-drawers, and a little Doublet of Canvas without ſleeves.</p>
            <p>That I may not be too tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in my Relation, We hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily arrived at <hi>Maltha;</hi> from whence a little while after I parted in a Veſſel that was bound for <hi>Provence,</hi> which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ten or twelve days ſail, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived moſt happily at <hi>Cioutat,</hi> my dear Countrey. I leave you to judg of the joy that I had therefore, after ſo long and ſo cruel a ſlavery. My Mother, who by chance was ſtanding on the ſhore-ſide when I landed, was ready to dye for joy ſo ſoon as I had made my ſelf known to her, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:39407:35"/>as ſhe ſaw me return back again alive, and in good health, after that ſhe had ſo many times bewailed me, as one that was dead.</p>
            <p>I admired the change that Fortune and Death had cauſed in that Town in a few years ſpace; ſome that I had left poor, were become rich; and many that were rich, were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come poor. The greater part of thoſe which I knew, were dead; and their place was filled up with others that I knew not at all, and whom I had left in their infancy, or ſuch as were not at that time born. In a word, All things in my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey appeared in another manner than was the Idea which I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in my mind of it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:39407:35"/>You may imagine perhaps (Gentlemen) that my Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are come to an end, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that I am returned to my Fathers Houſe, and that there is little likelihood that after I had eſcaped ſo great perils, I ſhould engage my ſelf another time in an occaſion of falling into the like again. But I told you that my Trade was to go to Sea, and thoſe that are accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to this ſort of life, are quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a weary of the Land, and know not how to employ them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves therein. The Dangers, the Traverſes, the Slaveries, Death it ſelf, which preſent themſelves ſo often to them, are ſo far from diſcouraging them, that on the contrary they ſeem
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:39407:36"/>to add I know not what kind of Charms that attract them the more. 'Tis a kind of life, full of various delights, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual changes; to day you ſee one Nation, to morrow another quite contrary in manners, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, cuſtoms, and religion; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Climates, different fruits and wines; and in a word, all is (as it were) new, and that is it which renders this Maritine life very divertizing; for as you know, man naturally loves al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration: How abundant and proſperous ſoever the fortune is which he at preſent poſſeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, if his life be not diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, even his own happineſs diſguſts him.</p>
            <p>Thus therefore I had not been
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:39407:36"/>long at <hi>Cioutat,</hi> taking my eaſe, but this repoſe cloi'd me, and I wiſhed for ſome occaſion to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it ſelf, that I might return again to Sea; in regard, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all this, I thought my ſelf fit for nothing upon land: At laſt I lighted upon a Veſſel, which was bound for <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drette;</hi> they took me in <hi>Pilot</hi> to conduct it: the Voyage was proſperous; and returning to my Country again, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Holland</hi> Veſſel ready to ſet Sale for <hi>Alexandria,</hi> I em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barqued my ſelf therein alſo, as <hi>Pilot;</hi> and we performed our Voyage hither in three Weeks time.</p>
            <p>Some days after our Arrival there, there came an order to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:39407:37"/>the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> from the <hi>Grand Signior,</hi> to lay an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bargo on all the Chriſtian Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels that were found at that time in the Port of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> that ſo they might make uſe of them to carry Men and Ammunition for one Voyage only. Thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of lading our Ship with Merchandize, to return back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain (as we hoped to do), our Ship was filled with Soldiers, to be carried to <hi>Rhodes.</hi> The Wind was favourable enough to us; we arrived there in few days.</p>
            <p>Having weighed Anchor, I underſtood that <hi>Murdhat</hi> my Patron, out of whoſe hands I had eſcaped, was at that time <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of that Iſle; and that he had his reſidence therein.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:39407:37"/>I confeſs that this news ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me, and aſtoniſhed me much; and I was yet the more troubled, when I was told, that he already knew (I don't know by what means) that I was in the Port.</p>
            <p>After that I had a little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered what I ſhould do in this encounter, knowing that I could not eſcape out of his hands, if he had a deſign of doing me any harm; I thought it better for me to prevent him, and to caſt my ſelf into the hands of his mercy, rather than to ſtay till he ſent for me; and that I might the better diſpoſe him to my pardon, I entreated a certain <hi>Turk</hi> of Quality, with whom I entred into acquaintance in our paſſage, to go to him a little
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:39407:38"/>before me, and to ſpeak to him in my behalf.</p>
            <p>Whilſt this <hi>Turk</hi> went to do me this good office, I borrowed of the Captain, and the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal men of the Ship, all that was worthy making a preſent of, engaging my ſelf to give them what money they deſired for it. I had alſo for my own particular ſome thing of curioſity; to wit, fine Linnen-Cloth, Glaſſes, a Watch, and ſome other knacks. I made them up all very neatly in a basket, which I carried up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my head; and in this equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page I went my way wirh a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to accoſt the <hi>Baſhaw.</hi> When I came near him, he was walking in a Gallery, and talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with ſeveral people that were
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:39407:38"/>round him: Being about two pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces diſtant from him, I laid my basket upon the ground, and kneeling down, kiſſed the hem of his Garment; ſaying to him, <hi>Sultan, I come to caſt my ſelf into your hands, with all that I am worth in the world, which you ſee in this basket; you are my Patron, diſpoſe of it all, and pardon me.</hi> Long while it was, that he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon me haughtily, without ſpeaking a word to me, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any ſign that I ſhould riſe up: At laſt ſhaking his head a little, and putting his hand on his ſide, <hi>Ah Cane, Cane!</hi> ſaid he to me; there he ſtopt (his eyes being fixed upon me), and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards addreſſing himſelf to them that were near him; <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:39407:39"/>hold a little</hi> (ſays he to them) <hi>how great the boldneſs is of this dog, to preſent himſelf to me, after the injury that he hath done me, in making me loſe my Galley. Call Iſſauf Aga hither to me,</hi> (purſued he) (this was his Lieutenant) when he was come, <hi>Well Iſſauf Aga</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>there's our man in our hands, what ſhall we do with him? Go, let them give him</hi>— At this word, <hi>Let them give him,</hi> I thought my ſelf a dead man, not doubting in the leaſt, but that it was the number of Baſtinadoes that he meant: <hi>Let them give him all that he ſtands in need of.</hi> Afterwards looking upon me kindly, with a ſmiliing countenance. <hi>Riſe up Lewis</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he) <hi>thou haſt done nothing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:39407:39"/>but what thou oughteſt to do; and I love thee the more for it, and I will ſhew thee as much, in doing thee good; although thou haſt made me loſe more than threeſcore thouſand Piaſters.</hi> He would needs know afterwards, in what manner I eſcaped the ſecond time, and all that happened to me afterwards. I told him the whole ſtory in particular, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all the adventure of the Night-Coat made him laugh, and he had the goodneſs, even to tell me, that when I had eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped out of the Galley, the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit</hi> (being an Officer) think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to puniſh me; after many threatnings, becauſe I did not return back again into my place at the Bench, gave great blows
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:39407:40"/>with his ſtick upon the Night-Coat, which making it to tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble down, he was greatly aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, when he ſaw that I was not under it.</p>
            <p>Afterwards I informed him in what a condition my affairs were; and having told him, that I was only Pilot in a Ship, he gave me a very fair <hi>Polacque,</hi> which he had in the Port, bidding me go, and get my livelihood with this Veſſel; telling me withal, that <hi>in whatſoever ports of the Sea I ſhould hear that he was, that I ſhould come to him, and that he would do me what good he could.</hi> Having ſaid theſe words, he went his way, and <hi>Iſſauf Aga</hi> carried me to dinner, and afterwards gave me the poſſeſſion of the <hi>Polacque,</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:39407:40"/>with which and the help of ſome Mariners, which were ſent me by the Captain of the Veſſel, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I was Pilot, we returned to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria,</hi> where having laden our Ship with what we had mind to, we ſet Sail towards <hi>France;</hi> &amp; at laſt happily arrived at <hi>Cioutat,</hi> continually praiſing and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the generoſity of ſo good a <hi>Patriot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word (Gentlemen) to conclude this Narration: I will cut ſhort, and only tell you, that two or three years were paſt, wherein making ſeveral Voyages to the principal parts of the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diteranian,</hi> I got with my <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacque</hi> ſome eſtate, and having learnt that the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, after his Term of being
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:39407:41"/>
               <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of <hi>Rhodes</hi> was expired, went to <hi>Tunis,</hi> to be <hi>Baſhaw</hi> alſo of that place; I reſolved to make a Voyage thither. I can't expreſs to you the kindneſs that he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me, and the good will that he teſtified to me, when I went to ſee him, all the Merchandizes that I laded my Ship with for my own ſhare, were exempt from pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ten in the hundred, being a Tax impoſed upon the exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Commodities, which all others paid. I laded my Veſſel with what I had a mind to, and for the height of his favour, he honoured me with a truſt, which never had, and it may be never will have its parallel, that is to ſay from a <hi>Baſhaw,</hi> towards a poor miſerable perſon, ſuch as
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:39407:41"/>my ſelf. This was (if I be not miſtaken) the third Voyage which I made to <hi>Tunis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There remained now not above ſix months of the three years reign of this Baſhaw. One day he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me to be called to his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and ſaid to me, <hi>Lewis, ſince I have been Baſhaw of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, I have got together good ſtore of money, which I have a deſign to ſend to</hi> Rhodes <hi>before my return thither, that ſo I may divide my E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, becauſe of the hazard of the Sea: and in regard there is no man in the world in whom I have ſo much conſidence as in thy ſelf, I put the better part of my Fortune in thy hands, without fearing any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidelity from thee.</hi> Afterwards he ſhewed me 50 ſmall Barrels with
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:39407:42"/>their heads open, which he told me was filled with Checquines, Sultanines, Piſtols, and Piaſters, and bade me to carry them to <hi>Rhodes,</hi> and to return back again as ſoon as I could conveniently.</p>
            <p>I endeavoured at firſt to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him therefrom, becauſe of the ſmall Forces which I had in my Veſſel, and the riſque that he would run in confiding in a man of ſo ſmall value as my ſelf; telling him, <hi>That I greatly wondred how he could confide in me, ſeeing that I ſhould ſcarcely be willing to anſwer for my ſelf in an affair where the Temptation was ſo violent, and the Fortune ſo great and ſo certain.</hi> But all my reaſons not prevailing with him, part I muſt.</p>
            <p>Thanks be to God, I perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:39407:42"/>the Voyage without any ill ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident; I conſigned the money at <hi>Rhodes,</hi> and returned to <hi>Tunis,</hi> where you may eaſily judg in what a manner I was received.</p>
            <p>This Generous Lord having entertained me for ſome days at his Houſe, at laſt gave me per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to return home; and that I might have occaſion to be ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of his Liberality all my life long, he cauſed my Veſſel to be laded with Grain and other Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, without coſting me one farthing.</p>
            <p>Thus did I now ſet ſail from <hi>Tunis</hi> with Goods enough to paſs the reſt of my life in a handſome manner. I already meditated with my ſelf of a fair ſettlement in my own Countrey; and though it was
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:39407:43"/>againſt my inclination, I project<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to ſtay and fix my ſelf therein. But I found by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence not long after, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of man are badly laid, when they have no other prop to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold them, but the inconſtancy of the Sea. Scarcely had we loſt the ſight of the Coaſts of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bary;</hi> but a great wind accoſted us with ſuch a fury, that though we had no other ſail but the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler one of the Main-maſt, we tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> in a day and a half.</p>
            <p>But this haſte was our miſhap; for when we were in ſight of <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> the ſtorm became ſo great, that not being able to keep up our ſails, nor to govern the ſhip, our Maſt and our Sail-yard being
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:39407:43"/>broken, we were caſt upon the Coaſt that is towards <hi>Via Regia.</hi> The Veſſel was ſhipwrackt, and all my Goods, and my ſine projects of Fortune, were ſunk down to the bottom of the Sea, being hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py enough in eſcaping my ſelf by ſwimming, with ſome of my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners.</p>
            <p>Having repaired my ſelf a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle on the ſhore ſide, I took my way toward <hi>Rome,</hi> where I had ſome friends. I learnt at my ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival, that the <hi>Pilot-Real</hi> of the Popes Galleys was dead; and for as much as I was in ſome reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the knowledg of Sea-af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, I obtained that place by the help of my Friends.</p>
            <p>I have performed this Office near upon four years, and ſhould
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:39407:44"/>have continued in it ſtill, but that hearing that our King had a deſign to re-eſtabliſh his Galleys as they were heretofore, I thought it my duty to leave all, to come and offer my Talent and my ſervice to my lawful Prince. This is it (Gentlemen) that brings me hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with this Paſsport of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and theſe Letters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation from Cardinal <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio</hi> to Cardinal <hi>Mazarine.</hi> And foraſmuch as I know that it is hard to come to the ſpeech of his Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, I was a looking as I walked along in the place, for ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance to counſel me what I ſhould do; and as I was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling my head about it, I did by good fortune meet with this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, with whom I lived here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:39407:44"/>ſome time at the Conſuls of <hi>Tunis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus Captain <hi>Lewis Marott</hi> finiſhed the recital of his Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: Some admired them; others praiſed <hi>God</hi> for his having deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd him from ſo many perils; and all of them offered to ſerve him in what they were able. Thereupon they parted, to go each one whither his Charge called him. And ſome Months after, <hi>Lewis Marott</hi> had (not without ſome difficulty) the Office of <hi>Pilot-Real</hi> of the Galleys of <hi>France</hi> beſtowed upon him, and was made known to the King of <hi>France,</hi> who honoured him with a very fair golden Medal, and gave him moreover a good ſum of money,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:39407:45"/>to put him in a condition of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him.</p>
            <p>Here let us-ceaſe, and without any further curioſity, let us leave him to enjoy this his laſt good fortune, which he hath ſo well deſerved.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 3. Line 19. Read that <hi>Marott,</hi> p. 5. l. 8. r. <hi>Cioutat,</hi> and ſo throughout. p. 7. l. 2. r. <hi>Baudrand,</hi> p. 25. l. 13. r. <hi>Ein challa,</hi> p. 26. l. 18. r. <hi>Ein challa.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:39407:45"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
